<d:preface version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
           xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
  <?dbhtml filename="preface/index.html" ?>
  <d:title>Preface</d:title>
  <d:para>
    This book is a natural successor of my C programming book. There is no
    about that data structures and algorithms is one of the most critical
    subjects in computer science. Computer programming has changed a lot in
    last few decades. Programmers typically do not implement basic data
    structures in real-world code but rather they use ready-made libraries
    which are of very high quality. However, that does not decrease the
    importance of the subject. The importance is same even though a lot in
    programming world has changed and there will be times when you would want
    to implement your own version of data structures and algorithms. Another
    point is that for a programmer this subject allows one to excercise his
    knowledge of programming language to various problems this subject offers.
  </d:para>
  <d:para>
    One of the critical learnings from this subject which you, the reader, will
    learn is complexity computation. I am sure that you will certainly
    appreciate the value of knowledge after learning it. I cannot put enough
    stress on the importance of data structures and algorithms. The application
    of data structures and algorithms is there in almost all branches of
    computer science without exception. Any program you write will involve some
    algorithm and data structure. The importance of data structure and
    algorithms can be found from the title of the book on the subject, written
    by one of the great programmers Niklaus Wirth who created several languages
    most famous being Pascal, <d:quote>Algorithms + Data Structures =
    Programs</d:quote>.
  </d:para>
</d:preface>
